What stops countries from nuking each
other? Deterrence. That is the key
concept. This grim logic, this balance
created by very destructive bombs that
split atoms. But in order for deterrence
to work, it can't just be the bombs. It
has to have some other important
ingredients. First up, your enemy has to
believe that you will actually,
credibly, fire back a nuke. What that
means is you got to have these things
ready to go at all times. Like in the
United States, the president is the sole
authority who can authorize a nuclear
strike. And legally, no one can veto his
decision. He could launch a nuke within
5 minutes using some special
authorization codes and relying on this
football. I know it's not a football.
It's a briefcase, but it's called the
nuclear football. And inside of this,
there's a phone and a scary black book
that lists out all of the potential
targets that the president could
authorize a strike on. How many people
would die, what the effect would be.
It's all right there, by his side all
the time. The next ingredient to
deterrence is the ability to hit back.
Meaning, if one nuclear country is able
to destroy all of your nukes in a
surprise attack, then the whole thing
falls apart. So you got to have more
than one nuke, and you kind of got to
spread them out and hide them. The US
does this by spreading its nukes out all
throughout the world and dividing them
up by delivery methods. Some are sitting
in these big underground silos that are
spread all across the middle of the
country. Others are sitting on airplanes
positioned all around the globe. And
then of course, we've got nukes lurking
in the depths of the ocean, sitting on
submarines. They can carry up to 20
missiles, each of them with multiple
warheads. Like the amount of destruction
capability designed into these weapons
is kind of unfathomable, and that's kind
of the point. It has to be so bad, so
easy to launch, that your enemy's like,
"Not messing with that." Anyway, these
different delivery systems are called
the nuclear triad. Russia has something
like it, too. China's kind of developing
their own triad. But where the rubber
meets the road is the last ingredient,
and this is where the mind games begin.
Red lines. You have to signal to your
enemy what they would have to do to
warrant an attack. The cleanest and
safest way to do this is to just say,
"Hey, we will not attack anyone with our
nukes unless they attack us with their
nukes first." Most countries operate
with this as their kind of de facto
policy. But for the two big dogs, Russia
and the United States, red lines are a
way for them to kind of play mind games
with each other because they believe
that it would incentivize their enemy to
do everything short of a nuclear attack.
Chemical weapons, conventional attacks,
all these other things that we also want
to deter. So, both of them keep their
red lines intentionally vague and fuzzy,
forcing each other to constantly be
questioning, "Where's the red line?
Like, am I going too far? Am I going to
trigger a nuclear strike if I do this or
that?" This keeps both sides very far
away from provoking each other. And this
is the mind game at the heart of modern
nuclear politics. It's a very dangerous
mind game, but it's nonetheless the one
we have.